<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<!DOCTYPE article  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.1/JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article dtd-version="1.1" article-type="book-review"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id>JFRR</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Journal of Folklore Research Reviews</journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="epub">2832-8132</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>IU ScholarWorks</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">37565</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>K. Brandon Barker - Review of Fragile Grounds: Louisiana's Endangered Cemeteries</article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                    <name>
                        <surname>K. Brandon Barker</surname>
                        <given-names/>
                    </name>
                    <aff>Indiana University</aff>
                    <address>
                        <email></email>
                    </address>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <pub-date publication-format="epub" date-type="pub" iso-8601-date="2021">
                <year>2019</year>
            </pub-date>
            <product product-type="book">
                <person-group>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Jessica H. Schexnayder and Mary H. Manhein</surname>
                        <given-names/>
                    </name>
                </person-group>
                <source>Fragile Grounds: Louisiana's Endangered Cemeteries</source>
                <series></series>
                <year iso-8601-date="2021">2017</year>
                <publisher-loc>Jackson</publisher-loc>
                <publisher-name>University Press of Mississippi</publisher-name>
                <page-range>148 pages</page-range>
                <price></price>
                <isbn>978-1-4968-1432-6</isbn>
            </product>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Reviewers retain copyright and grant JFRR the right of first publication with the review simultaneously licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution License that allows others to share or redistribute reviews with an acknowledgment of the review's original authorship and initial publication JFRR.</copyright-statement>
            </permissions>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <fig id="f0" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
            <alt-text>Overhead photo of flooded mausoleums.</alt-text>
            <graphic xlink:href="2249_schex.jpeg"/>
        </fig>    
        <p>The University of Mississippi Press’s America’s Third Coast book series, edited by Carl
            A. Brasseaux and Donald W. Davis, highlights the history, life, and culture of
            oft-ignored southern coastal areas. Jessica H. Schexnayder and Mary H. Manhein’s
                <italic>Fragile Grounds: Louisiana’s Endangered Cemeteries</italic> joins the series
            as a “visual treasury of [Louisiana’s] disappearing cemeteries and a call to preserve
            them” (back-cover blurb).</p>
        
        <p><italic>Fragile Grounds</italic> is a beautiful book with more than 250 high-gloss images
            presented across 148 pages. That is an achievement, but <italic>Fragile Grounds</italic>
            wants to be more than that. Schexnayder and Manhein want to yell into the void. The
            authors preface their book with a description of Louisiana’s coastal areas in dire
            straits: “Rapid advancement of coastal erosion combined with storm surges, rising sea
            levels, and compaction and sinking of the land have led to an unstable landscape. That
            instability is pushing Louisiana’s residents inland, forcing them to leave evidence of
            their histories, such as their cemeteries, behind” (xi). They face two antagonists: the
            oncoming of time that waylays all, and the specific environmental factors that speed up
            time’s processes in south Louisiana.</p>
        
        <p>The book divides into four chapters: The Law, the Lands, the People; South Louisiana
            Burial Customs; Select Coastal Zone Cemeteries; Select Cemeteries beyond the Coastal
            Zones; and it concludes with an afterword and three appendices, listing the documented
            cemeteries, immigration dates, and the dates of Louisiana hurricane landfalls between
            1851 and 2015. Throughout, photographs dominate the supplementary text.</p>
        
        <p>In chapter 1, Schexnayder and Manhein outline their early plans to gather global
            positioning system (GPS) data for the more than 500 cemeteries found in Louisiana’s
            endangered coastal zones. Understanding that other groups had taken single-point
            location data for coastal cemeteries in the past, Schexnayder and Manhein painstakingly
            mapped out GPS points “around the perimeter of each cemetery,” noting that these GPS
            points “will always be there, even when the land is gone” (7). Clearly, these cemeteries
            took priority because they lie within the realms of ongoing coastal erosion and land
            loss, but the authors quickly admit the shortcomings of their earliest intentions: “What
            initially began as an effort to capture global positioning system (GPS) point data for
            the state’s coastal zone cemetery boundaries quickly turned into a race against time to
            also document cemeteries that might be at risk for other reasons” (7). They add,
            “Originally capturing the actual size of the cemeteries was important, but we soon
            learned that the cultural dynamics of the various regions could not be ignored.”
            Satellites and their high-tech imagery—as all quick-access technology is wont to
            do—offered a tantalizing beginning, but Schexnayder and Manhein found themselves wanting
            (needing) to have their boots on the ground in order to complete their project.</p>
        
        <p>Chapter 2 orients us toward the view from the ground, presenting a typology of southern
            Louisiana’s burial types and customs. The first are inground burials, which the authors
            note are quite common “despite tales of water table woes” (13). Other examples, such as
            wall vaults, copings, and society tombs, are all well represented photographically. Each
            page features two to three images or one full-page image. They constitute a commendable
            selection of clearly framed shots—meant to exemplify type—alongside more artistic,
            subjective frames—meant to express character. One striking example is the full-page
            image that captures an open, weathered Bible, slowly disintegrating on top of an already
            dilapidated family tomb in New Orleans’s St. Louis I cemetery (27). Another half-page
            image shows an ornate wooden coffin in Denham Springs Memorial Cemetery surreally
            displaced by a recent storm surge, resting upside-down on top of some other soul’s
            headstone (30).</p>
        
        <p>Having cataloged the major types and customs, <italic>Fragile Grounds’</italic> latter
            half attends to localities, offering even more images alongside short, punchy historical
            anecdotes from thirty-seven cemeteries within the coastal zone (chapter 3) and six
            cemeteries lying beyond the coastal zone (chapter 4). While these anecdotes do not stand
            in for full, theoretical analyses of Louisiana’s burial customs and materials,
            intriguing nuggets of history and culture do rise to the surface. There is the mass
            grave of Isles Dernières that memorializes wealthy vacationers who were killed by a
            powerful hurricane in 1856 (102-4). There are the tragic, unmarked graves of slaves
            tended by Louisiana’s great novelist Ernest Gaines and his wife, Dianne Gaines, at Mount
            Zion River Lake Plantation Cemetery in Pointe Coupee Parish (117-9).</p>
        
        <p>In their afterword, Schexnayder and Manhein reiterate the futility of ongoing mitigation
            efforts (e.g., newly designed heavy concrete vaults, metal tie-down straps) meant to
            protect the cemeteries: “Such measures can only be successful if the land is stable, but
            the land is not stable” (125). Curtly, but poignantly, they criticize talk of moving the
            cemeteries to safer, more stable grounds as “imaginative, but not realistic,” adding,
            “The harsh reality is that we cannot save these burial sites; we can only document them
            before they are gone” (126).</p>
        
        <p>And so <italic>Fragile Grounds<italic> juxtaposes the image of these crumbling graveyards
                    against the oncoming of death, of time, and of disappearance. Schexnayder’s and
                    Manhein’s desire to yell into the void manifests as a gesture toward
                    inevitability. Commendable as their project is, they can do no more than offer
                    images of Louisiana’s stark, attractive, crumbling, and partially washed away
                    headstones, tombs, mausoleums, tabletops, and potter’s
            fields.</italic></italic></p>
        
        <p><italic><italic>
                    Stone markers on a wet, Southern ground.
                </italic></italic></p>
        
        <p>--------</p>
        
        <p>[Review length: 879 words • Review posted on October 3, 2019]</p>
        
        
    </body>
</article>
