<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<!DOCTYPE article  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.1/JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article dtd-version="1.1" article-type="book-review"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id>JFRR</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Journal of Folklore Research Reviews</journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="epub">2832-8132</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>IU ScholarWorks</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">37566</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>Jeffrey Tolbert - Review of Spiritualism in Nineteenth-Century New Orleans: The Life and Times of Henry Louis Rey</article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                    <name>
                        <surname>Jeffrey Tolbert</surname>
                        <given-names/>
                    </name>
                    <aff>Penn State Harrisburg</aff>
                    <address>
                        <email></email>
                    </address>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <pub-date publication-format="epub" date-type="pub" iso-8601-date="2021">
                <year>2019</year>
            </pub-date>
            <product product-type="book">
                <person-group>
                    <name>
                        <surname>Melissa Daggett</surname>
                        <given-names/>
                    </name>
                </person-group>
                <source>Spiritualism in Nineteenth-Century New Orleans: The Life and Times of Henry Louis Rey</source>
                <series></series>
                <year iso-8601-date="2021">2017</year>
                <publisher-loc>Jackson</publisher-loc>
                <publisher-name>University Press of Mississippi</publisher-name>
                <page-range>201 pages</page-range>
                <price></price>
                <isbn>978-1-4968-1008-3</isbn>
            </product>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Reviewers retain copyright and grant JFRR the right of first publication with the review simultaneously licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution License that allows others to share or redistribute reviews with an acknowledgment of the review's original authorship and initial publication JFRR.</copyright-statement>
            </permissions>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <fig id="f0" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
            <alt-text>Three people in 19th-century dress seated around a table.</alt-text>
            <graphic xlink:href="2259_dagge.jpg"/>
        </fig>    
        <p>Present-day students and scholars of supernatural belief in the United States cannot
            avoid engaging with the history and legacy of Spiritualism. The iconography of both
            popular culture and contemporary vernacular religious practices—from popular horror
            films to ghost-hunting groups to heterodox, unaffiliated practitioners, to say nothing
            of explicitly Spiritualist organizations—owes much to the emergence in the nineteenth
            century of Modern American Spiritualism, which, Melissa Daggett notes, was itself “a
            complex phenomenon whose philosophical roots reached back to Europe in the eighteenth
            century” (28).</p>
        
        <p>Daggett’s task in this work is to situate the life of Henry Louis Rey, a free person of
            color, in the context of mid-nineteenth-century New Orleans history: “Henry Louis Rey
            was the quintessential postbellum black political leader. He was thirty-three years old
            in 1865, French-speaking, a lifetime resident of New Orleans, a Saint-Domingue
            descendant from an elite Creole family, literate, fair-skinned, and a man who had honed
            his leadership skills as a captain in the Union Native Guards” (69). He was also a
            medium, and his communications with the spirit world intersected in complex ways with
            the other facets of his life.</p>
        
        <p>A main source of information on Rey’s activities are the extensive séance registers
            maintained by Rey and his fellow spiritualists for a period of almost twenty years,
            beginning in 1858. Against the backdrop of generalized racial unrest, the transition of
            the Afro-Creole community from a place of social power and prestige to one of
            undifferentiated (and despised) blackness after the Civil War, and the development of
            American Spiritualist practices through the middle of the century, Daggett traces Rey’s
            story, from his role as a spiritualist medium, a soldier (for both the Confederacy and
            the Union), an anti-racism activist in the postwar years, to his sad decline and death
            in a Jim Crow New Orleans quite different from his early days in the Afro-Creole
            ascendancy.</p>
        
        <p>Daggett’s historical detective work is impressive. Rey’s life story weaves in and out of
            the local, the national, and the spiritual strands of a larger historical discourse
            centered on the changing fortunes of free people of color in New Orleans. Spiritualism
            is less a focus of the work than the title might suggest, but Daggett convincingly
            connects the movement to politics and race relations in the nineteenth century.</p>
        
        <p>The story of Spiritualism in New Orleans emerges in fits and starts through a bewildering
            array of personages, events, and politics. Secondary strands discuss Swedenborg, Voodoo,
            Reconstruction, the Mechanics’ Institute Massacre, the governorship of Henry Clay
            Warmoth, and any number of other events, people, and political discourses. All of these
            are undoubtedly necessary to understand Rey’s life and Spiritualism’s role in it, but
            Rey himself sometimes disappears into the thick of things, as the reader is introduced
            to one medium, politician, or activist after another.</p>
        
        <p><italic>Spiritualism in Nineteenth-Century New Orleans</italic> is ultimately a history
            not of Spiritualism, and not entirely of Henry Louis Rey. Rather it is a history of New
            Orleans in several registers: the racial, the spiritual, the sociopolitical. All of
            these are useful reminders of the broader trajectory of American social and religious
            history in this troubled period. In her epilogue, Daggett writes, “Henry Louis Rey’s
            Cercle Harmonique disappeared in 1877, coinciding with the official end of
            Reconstruction” (149). She notes that this pattern was reflected at the national level,
            on which Spiritualism was replaced by other emerging religions. Daggett’s major
            contribution here is precisely this movement between the local and the national,
            illustrating the need to take seriously “nonmainstream” traditions that intersect in
            powerfully compelling ways with other aspects of vernacular experience.</p>
        
        <p>--------</p>
        
        <p>[Review length: 591 words • Review posted on April 19, 2019]</p>
        
        
    </body>
</article>
